Guide to the Michel Bégon Papers GEN MSS 1756
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Michel Bégon papers
circa 1651-1718
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Begon, Michel, 1638-1710
GEN MSS 1756
3.72 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
The collection contains correspondence, reports, journals, lists, pamphlets and broadsides, and other papers relating to Michel Bégon and French colonial administration in the Caribbean, French maritime commerce, foreign relations, domestic economic matters, and botany in the 17th century.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William S. Reese (Yale 1977), 2000, 2001. Purchased from William Reese Co. on the Library Associates Fund, 2001. Purchased from William Reese Co. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2002, 2013.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, Reports, and Other Papers of Michel Bégon, circa 1651-1718. II. Letters and Reports from Jean de La Mousse, 1690-1695. III. Description des Repas Espangnols et Collations qu'on a Donne a Monsieur Le Comte D'Estrées à Cadiz, circa 1700. IV. Extrait du Journal du Sieur Boureau Pour L'Amerique, 1689.
Michel Bégon (1638-1710)
Michel Bégon was a French colonial administrator during the Ancien Régime. He served as intendant of the Windward Islands from 1682 to 1684, and subsequently intendant of Saint-Domingue, where he became involved in the spice trade. After he returned to France in the late 1680s, he was appointed intendant of Rochefort (1688-1710), and in 1694, obtained the intendance of the généralité of La Rochelle. Bégon also was an amateur botanist.
Associated Materials
Other material by or relating to Michel Bégon (GEN MSS File 232, GEN MSS File 233, GEN MSS File 234) can be found by searching Orbis (Yale's Online Catalog).
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, reports, journals, lists, pamphlets and broadsides, and other papers relating to Michel Bégon and French colonial administration in the Caribbean, French maritime commerce, foreign relations, domestic economic matters, and botany in the 17th century.
Reports concern expeditions led by Jean d'Estrées and other French naval officers during the Dutch War and War of the Grand Alliance, voyages of French ships to Africa and the West Indies, and commercial and military activities of other colonial powers, particularly Spain. The collection contains intelligence profiles on Spanish mining and trade of silver and salt, as well as the movements, structure, and economics of the Spanish fleet. Several reports are addressed to French Navy Secretary Jean-Baptiste Colbert, Marquis de Seignelay, and some were compiled for Bégon in his capacity as intendant of Saint-Domingue, and later La Rochelle. Other topics of reports include French relations with the Vatican and political developments in the Ottoman Empire. Also present are decrees, publications, correspondence, and writings related to horse breeding in France, and trade of tobacco, sugar, and chocolate.
The collection additionally contains journals, correspondence, and reports of Jean de la Mousse, a Jesuit missionary living among the Kalina people in French Guiana; an account of Spanish food offered to d'Estrées in Cadiz; and a journal detailing the voyage of a French ship to the West Indies, which contains references to slavery and the slave trade.
Colonial administrators -- West Indies, French -- 17th century; France -- Colonies -- Administration; France -- Colonies -- Africa; France -- Colonies -- West Indies; Botany -- West Indies; Carib Indians; Dutch War, 1672-1678; Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697; Horses--Breeding--France--History--17th century; Indians of South America -- Missions; Salt industry and trade -- Spain; Silver mines and mining -- Mexico; Silver mines and mining -- Spain; Slave trade; Slavery -- West Indies, French.; Turkey--History--Ottoman Empire, 1288-1918; France -- Commerce -- 17th century; France -- Commerce -- 18th century; France -- Foreign relations -- Netherlands; Netherlands -- Foreign relations -- France; Spain -- Commerce -- 17th century; West Indies, French -- Commerce -- Early works to 1800; Colonial administrators; Begon, Michel, 1638-1710; Estrées, Jean, duc d', 1624-1707; La Mousse, Jean de, 1650-1699; Seignelay, Jean-Baptiste Colbert, marquis de, 1651-1690; Catholic Church ($x: Foreign relations); France. Marine; Spain. Armada
- Correspondence, Reports, and Other Papers of Michel Bégon, circa 1651-1718; 1; 2.34 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence, reports prepared by and for Michel Bégon, printed material, and other documents relating to French colonial administration and maritime commerce, the War of the Grand Alliance, activities of British and European navies, horse breeding in France, French papal relations, and the geography, manufactures, and agricultural production of the province of Auvergne. Included are a number of reports providing intelligence on the Spanish fleet in the Caribbean and Spanish commercial interests, such as salt and silver mines, tobacco, and silk. The series additionally contains a report on the Ottoman Empire from Constantinople (now Istanbul), a small amount of drawings and maps, and papers related to botany.
  Arrangement
  Materials maintain order found at time of acquisition.
  - Manuscript to-do list, circa 1675 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lettre a Mr. le Marquis de Seignelay par la concord, 1684 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Bégon reports that he arrived in Saint-Domingue to carry out the king's orders to survey the fortifications.
  - Manuscript copy of a letter sent by Bégon to an unidentified recipient, regarding affairs on Martinique, 1684 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Regarding a judicial appointment at Saint-Domingue.
  - Memoire de ce qui est Contenu dans la Boette envoyé a Mr. de Tildmont [?] par [illegible] de St. Preuil, circa 1685 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Memoires sur l'Auvergne, 1692 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Abregé du travail fait dans les monoyes, ouvertes tant en Louis d'or et Louis d'argent depuis les 1er. Octobre 1693 jusqu'au dernier Septembre 1697, que en solz, liards, et pieces de 4e pendant la premiere et seconde Reformation [and addendum] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - List of wines, liquors, and other trade items which passed through the port of La Rochelle, circa 1694-1700 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Mats de France, 1698 (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Manuscript account by French official reporting on his visit to Rome, relations between France and Pope Innocent XII, and the like, 1692 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Memoire sur les principales marchandises d'Alican, circa 1697 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Raisons que le Commerce a pour n'en registrer pas tout l'argent qu'on tire hors le royaume d'Espagne pour le transporter en France et autres pays etrangers, circa 1700 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Receipt signed by the Duke of Sully, 1718 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Notice des voies Romaines qui ont existé dans l'ancienne province de Bourgogne, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Etat du commerce des Pyrenées, circa 1690-1700 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Coppi collationée du don du Roi de l'ancien college, a la Compangnie avec 2000th sur le Domaine Decembre 1629, circa 1651 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Copie D'une Lettre En forme de Relation Éscrite de Constantinople Le 8.e De mars 1688 à un Ami De Smyrne (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Unsigned copy of an intelligence report to a French agent in Smyrna (now Izmir), which discusses the reign of the newly crowned Sultan Suleiman II, activities of the Grand Vizier, ministers, and janissaries, and politics and unrest in Constantinople and elsewhere in the Ottoman Empire.
  - Regarding a matter dealing with a merchant of La Rochelle and American trade of products including tobacco and chocolate, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Depuis la revolte du prime Soubasin qui fut en l'année 95…, 1697 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Memoire su Les droits de Consuls de la nation francoise qui sont en Espagne, 1698 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Memoire de ce qu'on peut aporter de Cartagene (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Pour les pauvres Honalis de Blois…, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Account in Bégon's hand showing monies allotted to impoverished people in Blois, the church, and individuals
  - Memoire pour faire voir a Monseigneur le Marquis de Seignelay le profit que sa Majesté retirera par le moyen du secret de rendre leaüe de la mer doulce…, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Memoire du Commerce qui se peut[?] a la Coste de L'ocean de Barbarie, a Saló, Saffy, et a St. Croix, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Articles et fleurs a tirer de Provence, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - La gumme blanche & sêche…, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Considerations sur le commerce de la ville de Nantes que ses negociants suplient monseigneur l'intendant de represanter au conseil du roy en leur faveur, circa 1700 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Memoire de ce qui est contenu dans la boete de hetre que [j'ai] donne a Capt. Fage, circa 1685 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    A list of American goods sent by an unidentified party to Bégon, M. de Villermont, and the Reverend Father Prior of Poitiers. Included in the list are vanilla pods, fruits, alpaca wool, manatee bones, and various Indigenous artifacts.
  - Manuscript plan for a parterre garden, circa 1700 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Contemporary manuscript copy of plans to organize a French trading company with interests in the West Indies, Canada, and New Spain, 1682 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Memoire sur l'arsenal de Cadix et de l'estat present de la marine d'Espagne, circa 1700 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Memoire sur les salines d'Espagne salines de Cadiz, circa 1710 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Memoire sur les officiers de mer des espagnols, circa 1700 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Manuscript table of French ships' flags, also noting flags of foreign nations, circa 1680s (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Collection of six French manuscript versions of two reports regarding silver mines in the West Indies and Spain compiled circa 1690-1700 for French administrators concerned with finance, commerce, and trade, circa 1690s (Box 3, Folder 29)
    References both Indigenous and African mining workers.
  - Collection of manuscripts relating to Michel Bégon's botanical interests, circa 1680s (Box 3, Folder 30)
    In addition to various writings on botany and medicine, the materials include a list of items Bégon hoped to procure for his West Indian cabinet, such as birds and bird eggs, feathers, turtles, snakes, and mats made from porcupine quills by Carib Indians.
  - Manuscript copy of a letter sent by Bégon to an unidentified recipient, regarding affairs on Martinique, 1684 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Coppie de lettres patentes du Roy portant don de 2000th sur le petit Brevet novembre 1640 et registrées en la Chambre des Comptes le 11e. Mars 1641 au Bureau finances a Poitiers le 9 decembre 1649 et en Parlement le 18 mars 1651, circa 1700 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Memoire pour servir d'instruction au Sr. Galifet lieutenant de marine comandant la flute du Roy nomme Le Large, Memoire du Roy par la fregate du Roy La [illegible] [in Bégon's hand], 1684 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Coppie de la lettre escripte par Mr. Allegre a ses soeurs de renoures le 15 avril 1663 et par elles receve le 10 aoust suivant (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Regarding a pilgrimage to the Holy Land.
  - Autograph letter, signed, from the Jesuit Paul Bodin, to his unnamed superior regarding the martyrdom of a young female Muslim convert, 1697 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Bodin, a Jesuit missionary in Africa, reports on Fatmé, a young woman who converted from Islam to Catholicism and was subsequently murdered by her family.
  - Manuscript map illustrating a shoreline and shoals, possibly in French West Indies, circa 1685 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Traduction d'une lettre escrite d'Espagne a un seigneur du Perou et surprise dans un vaisseau pris par des armateurs francois dans la Mer du Sud [by "François de Colmenaves"], 1692 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Memoire sur le Change de Cadix pour les pays etrangers au mois de 7bre 1698, et sur le Commerce des piastres (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Relation de ce qui s'est passé pendant la Campagne des vaisseaux du Roy commandés par monsieur le Comte [Jean] D'Estrées, 1698 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    Related to a three-month cruise by a French naval squadron off the Spanish coast. D'Estrées describes interactions with Spanish officials such as Francisco Fernández de la Cueva Enríquez, the health of King Charles II, the Spanish fleet, and relations between France and Great Britain.
  - Journal de la croiziere dest et ouest entire ouessan et livuoise par ordre de Monsieur le Mareschal [Jean] Destrée, 1692 (Box 6, Folder 86)
    Report on a French coastal patrol under the command of Jean d'Estrées during the War of the Grand Alliance.
  - Memoir sur le commerce de Cadiz et les marchandises quon y peut envvier, circa 1685 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Ordonnance portant defenses de tout commerce estranges dans les isles francoises de l'Amerique; Ordonnance portant defences aux propres des vaisseaux bastis, dans les isles francoises des l'Amerique, et de la nouvelle France, de trafiquer dans les pais estrangers, 1670–1671 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Arrest, du conseil pour interdire aux estrangers le commerce des isles de l'Amerique, 1668 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Articles d'accord touchant la redition du fort de Pondichery [India], 1693 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Copy of treaty signed by Francois Martin of the French East India Company, and Lawrence Pit, who represented the Netherlands, after the town was captured by Dutch forces in 1693.
  - Memoire pour Monsieur de Bégon intandant des galleres du Roy a Marseille touchant le fil et taba qu'on peut tirer de l'Amerique faite Monsieur Jean Ange Manfredino Genois, circa 1685-1689 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Memoire sur le tabac d'Espagne, 1685 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Arrest portant que les passeport pour les vaisseaux francois qui irons aux isles de l'Amerique devont donné par le Roy, 1669 (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - Memoire sur le depart et l'arriveé des gallions et flottes, circa 1690 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Copie du memoire pour Monseigneur le Marquis de Seignelay du fort du Port Paix le 29 Aoust 1690; extrait de la lettre de Monsieur de Cussy a Monsr. le Comte de Blenac (Box 6, Folder 89)
    Report compiled by a military officer for French Navy Secretary Jean-Baptiste Colbert, Marquis de Seignelay, regarding events in Saint-Domingue and other French settlements in the Caribbean, including naval activities related to the War of the Grand Alliance. The report is accompanied by an extract of letter from Saint-Domingue Governor Pierre-Paul Tarin de Cussy to Charles de La Roche-Courbon, le Comte de Blenac, who was governor of Martinique at the time.
  - Manuscript memoir of M. La Vallier des Roches, French naval officer, spanning thirty years of French involvement in the near East, Africa, and the Americas, 1690 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    Includes descriptions of the march of French soldiers to Hungary before the battle of St. Gotthard during the Austro-Turkish War; the seizure of the Dutch colonies of Gorée in Africa, and Tobago, and the sinking of ships in the French fleet on the way to attack Dutch Curacao in 1678; a naval reconnaissance voyage off the coast of Central America in 1682; demonstration by the French fleet off the coast of Copenhagen in 1683; and the battle of Beachy Head during the War of the Grand Alliance.
  - Memoire ou journal de ce qui s'est passé abord du Faucon Anglois, commande par le Sr. Petit, depuis son départ des rades de La Rochelle...a son arriveé au fort rojal de la Martinique, 1705–1706 (Box 6, Folder 90)
    Journal kept by Malescot de Coulomiers, the King's scrivener, on a triangular voyage of the English Falcon, captained by Gilles Petit; the ship launched from La Rochelle, France, in September 1705, and sailed to the coast of Africa, arriving in Martinique in July 1706. The report describes Petit's attempted privateering, and violence perpetrated by the crew on African tribes, particularly women, burning villages and attacking, killing, and abducting African people.
- Letters and Reports from Jean de La Mousse, 1690–1695; 2; 0.21 Linear Feet
  Biographical / Historical
  Jean de la Mousse was a Jesuit missionary who arrived in French Guiana in 1684.
  Letters and reports from Jean de La Mousse to Michel Bégon and M. de Villermont. Some items are in La Mousse's hand, and others are in the hand of a copyist. Topics include La Mousse's missionary work with the the Kalina people and his impressions of their customs, events in Cayenne and other French settlements, the killing of Cayenne Governor Charles Poncet de Brétigny in 1645, and agriculture and commerce in the Caribbean. He also discusses the Royal African Company and the slave trade, and free Black people in the West Indies, as well as French colonial interests in North America and relations with the Iroquois.
  - Lists and inventories of materials in Series II (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Untitled letters and reports, circa 1693, undated (Box 4, Folder 47-58)
  - Continuation du journal de la Mission de la Magdelaine a Tulery en terre ferme a 15 lieües de Cayenne depuis le 15 Octobre 1690, 1690–1691 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Continuation du journal du Pere de la Mousse a la Mission de la Magdelaine de Tulery chés les Galibis de terre ferme a 16 lieues de Cayenne, circa 1691 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Lettres du Père de la Mousse jesuite à Cayenne addressée à Mr. de Villermont 1693 à 1694, et 1695 [cover sheet], circa 1695 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Lettre du P. de la Mousse Jesuite a Mr. de Villermont, 1692–1693 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Letters from Father de la Mousse to Mr. de Villermont, 1694 (Box 4, Folder 63-66)
  - Letter from Father de la Mousse to Michel Bégon, 1691 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Letter from Father de la Mousse to Michel Bégon, 1692 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Letters and reports from Father de la Mousse to Michel Bégon, 1693–1694 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Letters and reports from Father de la Mousse to Michel Bégon, 1694 (Box 4, Folder 70-74)
  - Letters and reports from Father de la Mousse to Michel Bégon, 1695 (Box 4, Folder 75-78)
- Description des Repas Espangnols et Collations qu'on a Donne a Monsieur Le Comte D'Estrées à Cadiz, circa 1700; 3; 0 Linear Feet (Box 4, Folder 79)
  Manuscript and corrected copy of a report on Spanish food served to Jean D'Estrées in Cadiz.
- Extrait du Journal du Sieur Boureau Pour L'Amerique, 1689; 4; 0 Linear Feet (Box 5)
  Extract from the diary of Martin Boureau recounting a voyage from Dunkerque, France to the Caribbean in a ship commanded by Captain Pierre de Latre. Topics include Saint-Domingue Governor Pierre-Paul Tarin de Cussy and other colonial governors, Spanish and Dutch traders, conflicts in the region, activities of the Brandenburg African Company, and trafficking abducted Africans. The journal also makes note of other ships, such as a frigate from Vlissigen, Netherlands, and a flute from Brandenburg-Prussia.